good luck
hello everybody I'm ready yes
we are in it is January 23rd
2023. we're here in active inference
guest stream number 34.1 with aval
guadin carlu we're going to have a one
hour presentation physics of creation
can the free energy principle ground the
construction of physical state spaces
followed by about an hour discussion so
if you're watching live please feel free
to add questions in the live chat and
we'll also have some guests so thank you
AFL for joining and off to you for the
presentation
hello
so this is a
complete presentation uh I will first
introduce myself in the work I am here I
have a common physics I'm working
creative sense under version of Andy
Clark
um this work is institutionally speaking
the product of Kairos research which is
laboratory which myself Alexi rozovski
who is present here today A lot of
people are funded to investigate issues
of events to political through political
Evolution and Community science
um and the the topic will be on the
physics of creation
uh so creation is a atypical term let us
say it will be contextualized in
presentation but let us first Define
that
it corresponds to the construction of
physical possibilities
physical spaces to talk in a more
technical language
and the original question that motivated
This research is whether or not
the federal principle a piece of math
that emerging the cognitive sounds which
we will get to very soon
is capable of representing the this
process of creation
so first I have tried the first run of
this without getting into the technicals
it did not work so I will address the
technicals first we will see some
Concepts in physics what they do how
they work how they relate to
[Music]
what people typically do in physics and
first I'd like to take a look at how
physics explain so physics explain with
laws they think that in nature you have
laws and those laws are basically formal
statements that constrain the possible
states of a system
and typically those are entirely lows
that from which you can derive logically
what the system will do an example of
natural entailing law is
Maxwell's equation of electromagnetics
it is a different Maxwell than the one
that is here
so what you see is four bits of
vectorial calculus that will tell you
how two fields
um later collectively the
electromagnetic field evolve
with regard to another so so this is a
formal constraint on what e and B can do
like the equality Express constraint by
definition and those can be used to
derive basically fully e and B given
boundary conditions which is how you do
things in electromagnetism
uh but what is of ravens here is that
any of the slope responses basically
that I can Define e as a virtual field
so it preciposes what is called set
space which is mathematical space that
represents a set of possible States
before I State Delta e and Delta B is
equal to this and this we have to state
that e exists
and he can take such and such States in
that case it is a vectoral space in
three dimensions
um and this headspace basically it has
by construction to capture any
difference that make a difference about
the system that is targeted
for any change in E to be basically
computable by math Theory it has to be
represented in the state space so by
construction I want this space to
categorize every variable of interests
in my system given this scope and
measurement capabilities of my theory
foreign
you have underlying notion that is
basically implicitly uh underlying the
notion of flows and the space that is
notion of symmetry
I cannot get into the query detail here
but I will try to be as complete as
possible
um we typically understand physical
theories outside specifically relativity
Theory and some weird Quantum stuff
uh to derive from symmetries symmetries
are I will say it out loud algebraic
rope of transformation over the set
space that do not affect the system's
Dynamics as granted as its laplacian
you don't have to understand what I just
said what you have to understand is that
there are ways in which I can transform
the system which does not change what it
is an example in symmetries the sailing
of the Lord falama skin in trial you see
that you are physically the same pattern
that is repeated again and again and
again and again gradually so if I uh
make a small rotation uh in either
direction it will not change a theme
and if I repeat it and repeat it and
repeat it and repeat it and repeat it
and repeat it I will still change my
system like formally I will apply
transformation but it does not challenge
basically what observable properties the
system have
and this is what asymmetry is it is a
set of transformation that is related by
a subset of smaller transformation and
that does not change what your system
observably is
and because of this symmetries are a
system that basically constrain what
difference can make a difference about
the system
so implicitly when I from light uh low
or set space I make a statement about
the underlying symmetries I make the
statements that
basically
everything that is not in the system
that is not represented as part of the
system
is something that is symmetric that the
system is Centric with regard to but
on which any transformation will not
affect the system trajectory at least
not in a way that is relevant to my
theory
um it works for physics because it looks
like in physics we have a few symmetries
that are everywhere verified that are
fundamental in some sense
it doesn't work so well in life in mind
because we don't have that
to be specific living system of a
structure
I do not think it should be
controversial and they have constitutive
symmetries they have changes that will
not affect them if I switch all of the
carbon atoms in my body I scramble them
between each other while keeping the
relation to the rest it did not change
the thing so it is very trivial in sense
of symmetry but basically every
structure
that is me entails symmetries and
Taylor's information that are possible
that do not affect the structure and
others are told affect it
and
this Authority is not a given like
symmetries are considered to be in
physics it is actively reconstructed by
the activity of me if I cut myself if I
fall if my bone break I will regrow
basically you will have seek official
tissue that will uh occur and that will
make it okay again and it will change
what structure is my body
most importantly
I I did I was not born that way like big
and with a bird and with 80 kilo of
meats I grew and I Grew From one single
cell and this single cell just created
anatomyal structure
um apparently X nilo from basically
genetic code and the context
and not only that but
life you know if itself evolves in a way
that builds structures that builds
symmetries
and a lot of this means that you can't
set a state space that is the space of
life in general of any living system the
Symmetry is that in the live system they
change to time
and they change by the own activity of
this system
so any living system construct set
spaces and to account for it we need a
theory of test-based construction
this is the motivation of the physics of
creation uh line of work and this is
basically the I did not permit as a
question it is the question that will uh
that you need to keep in mind in this
discussion
so uh Danielle do we have any question
yet
okay no technical issue that I should
know about
okay
so what we'll do is First Look at
basically what we say of Creation in
life in mind at the conceptual level
what is the history of the concept and
what they are going to do
when we look into the
formal specifics of how we
try to recruit to represent basically
recognition as inference and what limits
these attempts have
um and finally
um
we will take the reflection further and
see whether we can and how far we can
represent
physical creation the construction of
physical reality uh with the tentative
formalism we have framed here
so let us look at Creation in life and
mind
historically the term of creation it
refers to autopoiesis that is that means
literally self-creation and that is not
attempt by an activist what became an
activist so mainly uh the materana and
Varina to ground the study of cognition
the study of biology and the way well
analytic system work
um
they framed Orthopedic Theory as
basically the idea that cognition is
grounded in a way that link system
constructs itself like their metabolism
allow them to reconstruct a structure
and the structure does not have to be
conserved by metabolism so you have
self-creation and this is basically the
concept that try to articulate to ground
cognitive science and later uh very well
we and colleagues
try to basically concretize this by
working on how the cognition was enacted
which is it is implemented in the in the
body in the concrete activity of living
systems
and this basically um
was very determinant in the history of
cognitive sense and it framed the
4E approach so the extension of ignition
beyond the brain let us say very very uh
tentatively
uh the idea that
frame is that you have uh you can see
the diagram that is taken from the
Paulo's work and I tried to um
to explain the relation between
self-constitution so let us say it is a
weaker lighter more specified version of
the phrases and agency the idea is that
you have self-constitution that is the
fat living system build themselves and
it is basically afforded by the way
living system coupled with environments
and agencies uh lighter higher order of
regulation of this disability to define
basically the terms of your coupling
with
the environments
and
um
the ID generates is that living systems
there are systems that have a structural
identity that they actively generate and
sustain under precarious circumstances
there is no
benevolent universe that tells lives
that help life be life life has
basically to generate environment where
it is life and in doing so it generates
and it sustains
what it is its identity and all of this
is necessary for sense making so let us
say cognition to be something to occur
and
um
this is
in my opinion and in
um
to some extent in the power of our
opinion somewhat were deep it is a lot
of Concepts a lot of Greek words and
people have tried to frame this in a way
that is more mathematical and formal
and
the question
it generates is how to formalize these
self-creative property of biological
organization and cognition
and in a way that is basically grounded
in a material information flow in things
that are
concrete physical structure
we have a pretty good answer to that
actually we have a pretty good work that
made a point that you had related this
somewhat high-level concept to basic
physical processes this work is the work
of Moreno mosio and monteville mainly
who work in a forgot the name but uh
Institute eventually in the pay Basque
in Spain
and the idea is that living systems are
constituted by a closure of constraints
so the constraint is physical thing that
shape how other physical things work
very simple if I have air in a box that
is closed the air count with the box it
is constraint okay and the property that
individuates living things
is the fact that they are they are
considered by a set of constraints that
canalize metabolism in a way that
reconstructs the same way the same
system
of constraints
and so uh from there you have
self-constitution you have also um
structural let us say notion of biology
that does not depend on the matter it is
made of but on the way it is sustained
that is I think pretty good if you want
to have a physicalist notion of life
and
um
we have a very basic ontology in which
constraints they shape metabolism and
just shape information flow as in the
way uh living stem rug to things and
that grounds the autonomy of living
things the fact that they can recreate
themselves basically
but nothing gives a clear link between
this and cognitive meaning or anything
we could recognize as cognition
so this is what we will try to
articulate next
so how driven systems as we just defined
can create meaning
the notion I would like to import is the
notion of active inference which
I will not get into the mathematical
detail here but the idea is that the way
the flow the dynamical flow literally
that is untailed by an agent and its
environment it individuates states that
are being full basically an agent will
predict in a relatively familiar sense
um Sensations that it will
I don't always say that not perceived
Percy but undergo and actions it will
Undertake and these predictions are
basically what's underlying meaning for
the agent it underlies what states will
just swap into shape its own action and
be meaningful to them
Um this can be framed by in a pretty a
simple poetic move
uh by setting that biological
interactive systems they do not simply
infer what is they bring about uh their
own reality by actively inferring what
is Meaningful to them by actively
looking for states that they think are
will even fault their own structure and
then you start to have a stronger
relation between uh what a physical
system of constraint is and how it
invigorates states that are meaningful
but you still don't have a formal theory
of basically how this metabolic flow
builds
uh learning or creation like builds a
new states of possible a new space Sorry
of possible States that is not the one
it began with
uh
I had I have a description of a
structure that is the set of constraints
and this produces basically an activity
of the system a flow over the structure
and this flow is somehow constrains or
shape the structure the system takes at
time t plus one which itself produce a
new function a new flow etc etc etc
so it is this Dynamic of
um I don't want to call that cell for
functional unfolding whatever the the
way uh
a system of constraints produce a flow
that three produces the same constraints
that we want to formalize
and
um the question we could reframe as such
and we could reframe as how does
cognition the ability to understand
integrates information about the world
it can acts within biological
organization
because cognition is basically the flow
of political organization but this isn't
held by it everything that I see
is something that I but to say bring
about that I look at because of the
biological constraints I am
and therefore the question of creation
can be reframed as how the meaning I
project into the world is brought back
to shape my my own structure
and this is what we will try to frame
mathematically
um in the framework of active inference
uh Daniel any questions
so the
attempt that we make here is to see if
we can how basically we can represent
creation uh the process of inference
which is likely the most minimal highly
recognizable way a quick frame cognition
as something that is distinct from
Simply it's much of an implementation
uh let us look at a piece of math that
is called The Foundry principle and that
is the formal motivation of rounding for
achieving friends
it will be the hard part for people who
do not do maths or people who are not
already familiar with uh principle I
will work with slowly
which is a piece of math that frames
statistical in France from the medical
System Theory chemical System Theory is
basically the idea that you have States
and they move as a function of each
other
and what the fep does is to prove that
if I have something that is called a
Markov blankets so boundary
that's
any information must travel through for
two subsystem to communicate practically
then you have a synchronization that
emerged between states that are outside
this boundary and states that are inside
this boundary
and not only this but if I measure the
basically
um
every state that is on the inside of the
boundary entails belief and titles equal
distribution over the external States
and the flow of internal States is such
that it minimizes the international
distance between the actual Excel States
well so what I can observe and what I
believe to be the case where I of course
is the internal systems
so that was abstract
the basic unformal meaning of this
is that if I have a chemical system and
I have a boundary that acts to mediate
information exchange between two
supports then both the parts can
basically represent each other and hold
belief in each other in a way that is
constructed by the systematic
synchronization across the boundary it
is uh quite abstract and quite minimal
but it is a foul proof that we can have
representation kind of cognitive meaning
uh from a very very minimal set of
hypotheses which is basically a
consistent causal structure
and it is a pretty good case that
uh basic technical system for example
staff constraints constraint will
emerging robots this kind of very basic
non-cognitive things can entail
cognition
um
it has been argued that it does underlie
agency and creativity and similar
Concepts that
wouldn't tell in my opinion creation as
a prerequisite
so I will try to see whether the fep
actually can
represent creation as the
ability for agent to individuate states
that are spinning to them
um
the thing is that the existence of work
of bronchitis is monstrated for any
complex stochastic chemical system so
chemical systems that are random
and this transmission realized as
basically something that moves in
function of itself Plus
random noise it is a variable
formulation
I really
any thing that exists can be framed as
such
so we should be optimistic for the
ability of this
our reason to represent the cognitive
the production of creative meaning by
basic biological system and therefore
creation
which is another case because when I
frame uh something as X of t equal
something something well I have to
purify next we have to define
space of states that is X
and
I have defined creation as the ability
to construct basically physical
possibilities
so by construction if you frame
something within the medical System
Theory you have to individual states a
priority what you have written down is
not Croatian it can be a grunt operation
can be interesting in the city of
creation it is not creation it is not
the construction of physical spaces and
it is likely not the construction of
cognitive meaning at least in the sense
that an activist and
Auto poetic Theory people minutes
Justin writes what become measurable for
a given subsystem within the stochastic
chemical system which is a lot that is
not again creation
let us think about how
we should go we should think of the
preparation
um
there will be more math here I'm afraid
but the first system is to observe
another system
it will have to lose information about
its broader environment it is uh pretty
easy well it is a something can derive
from first principle
uh because basically
um if you frame it as a Quantum system
observation will entail entanglements by
definition I observe a system and it
becomes something that tells in the
States because
I become entangled with it
so it started to become physically
synchronized with my States but I cannot
synchronize with everything all the time
so if I
act so as to have more knowledge about
the object
I act so as to have less knowledge about
my environment
so there is no basically lossless
observation it is something that can be
derived in the content setting that can
be reframed in other way in classical
settings because of the way observation
will either induce heatings information
loss or cause myself to forget
information you can pretty much derive
it in a variety of case it is likely
true in all cases
and it means that
observation
as it is constrained by by on Flow and
the Y couple of the environment
it does not simply entails the
observation of pre-existing while
invigorated physical States it brings
about well the integrating the
well-defined survivals for me to observe
so
the way how to say
and given this it is hard maybe not
possible to frame a theory of
observation
from a mathematical theory that entails
a very well integrated physical States
if I frame such a theory of observation
or measurement of cognitive meaning it
will not be General and
I pretty much have to work creation on
the on the very fundamental
scales at which my theory operates
and this is something that is arguably
done by uh reframing of The Foundry
principle in for generic Quantum systems
by mainly Chris fields
the idea is to use
um category theoretic equivalence
between
lots of things I will definitely not get
into that
to reframe the synchronization Dynamic
that's in view
that builds cognitive meaning according
to the Friendship principle has a series
of binary measurements are equivalently
symmetry bracking operators
so the way a chemical system
synchronized with its environments under
the Feb
is reframed here as basically a series
of binary questions that I ask my
environment and
that enforce my interaction with it in
such a way that the answer to my
questions become physical facts
which you can derive from a rather
General
Quantum information Theory background
but that gives basically no structure
whatsoever to the measurement nothing in
this series says what kind of system can
ask what kind of questions
and this means that okay this drives
creation maybe drives the situation of
physical possibilities physical
observables
but it does not constrain at all what
discretion is so it doesn't explain much
and doesn't help much to understand how
a living system will create itself
um so we still have
somehow to recruit uh the cognitive and
the medical formulation of the fep that
I
discussed very tentatively earlier
so let us take things from there
um I have turned uh during this formal
discussion from the notion that we have
to represent Creation in the living and
cognitive world to the notion that
somehow it is necessary it was on
creation of physical reality like
the underlying states of physics
this third part with this third part
will serve mainly to discuss this claim
and what it means and
what we should do with it particularly
first
um I want to talk basically the decline
that
there is no a priority physical where it
is a pretty basic claim it should not be
treated as exceptional it is necessary
property of a coherent physics
it is necessary require property
actually of the formulation or
description of a world that is beyond
what we call metaphysics
let us be more specific in the
argumentation
I call
these argument from ontological
consistency
anontology that is naturalistic that
serves to present nature if it is
consistent cannot call onto external
object objects that will not be natural
to explain the properties of its own
objects for example if I tell you um
this thing is black because it reflects
uh the light in such and such way
and I can also explain the properties of
light it is self-consistent if I tell
you this thing is black because God will
eat and I cannot explain you what God is
physically it is not self-consistent
there is no the property that is
um
framed by Alexi rozanski who is present
here as the property of self-functional
consistency that is that the Anthology
should basically include itself
um the discourse we have on physics is
unless
we are very radical position about the
relation between human and the other
world it is something that exists in
nature and that is something that we
need to account as
an element of nature
these entail two things
this one's one thing actually it entails
that uh
scientific presentations the models and
Theory we have and the property of those
model and Theory have
they must be accounted for As Natural
entities in their own rights and there
they must be at least in principle
neighbors by the tools of physics and
science
and these entails in turn that
I cannot have such a thing as a law
asymmetry or a set space that pre-exist
physics
any statement I make about physics must
itself be explained by physical
processes
I will elaborate
on what it means uh the view of
physicist is typically that real
theories and those theories are
representation of the world that just so
happen to account for fundamental
structure of the world for example we
have the Maxwell law of electoral
magnetics
electromagnetism and those laws are
representations of a force that exists
and that is directed by um
as you want I think by a symmetry in the
hamiltonian sorry um
asymmetry in the quantum property of
systems but this symmetry practiced
basically any attempt to represent an
any physical process it is a fundamental
property what I say is that you cannot
have a fundamental property you can't
have something that predates physics and
that's
cannot ultimately be explained
and if you admit such a thing your
ontology is not consistent because you
have to admit some things that are
beyond that predate nature to explain
things in nature which is
the opposite of what self-consistency is
so
if I want to frame a world where you do
not have explanation that call unto
things that are Beyond physics
you have to have lost symmetries in the
species that are constructed by physical
processes
and it is not a promatic view to have at
least epistemologically it is necessary
let us discuss what it means concretely
um
we have cognitive systems
dot creative systems they perceive and
this perception brings about
collectively relevant states which the
cognitive agent experience as real
we have physical observers this physical
observers bring about what we call
punter states that are well invigorated
States
that are miserable and those States
constitute physical reality at least as
any given Observer can experience it
what I say here is that
this is not epistemic Notions
the important States and the cognitively
relevant states that perception
um
The cognitively Driven State under
perception by agents they are real and
they are invigorated as real by their
observation
and if we frame it properly
the qivp at least what we could do with
the qivp it represents how protamines at
least particles agents that have
properties that we classically
understand as mindful
they individuate physical observable
which means that they create the species
which means that this is a theory of
creation not simply a theory of how
access reality
but a theory of how we get reality in
the first place
and
to do anything like grounding properly
this claim it will take a lot more
details
and
I will try to work by showing
what the search and Theory would do
because obviously I do not have such a
theory that is frame formally from start
to finish as of now and if I did I will
not present it now
let us look at the way constraint
basically creates the relative
experience
this is a diagram of how as human
management from the world the social
world
basically we understand things like
constraints over what we do and can do
and what it entails I understand that if
I talk to you in proper English you will
understand if I talk to you in French
Australia you will not understand
understand that if I address it will be
inappropriate and if I hold myself in a
certain way it will lead you to believe
me more or less understand that if I
start speaking very loud it will disturb
people and they will act for me to stop
talking very loud I understand very
basic facts about how this world work
and I understand how this constrain the
action I can take and the consequences
of that action what experiences
basically a social cultural landscape
which exists uh independently from me
and that I act Within
and
what I claim is that
this social cultural landscape evolves
in a way that is creative that is
basically abuse new Norms exist that did
not exist 10 years ago and that is even
more true for one million ago or before
human worth seeing
and the way I can represent how I don't
tried to understand this social
landscape
and possibly fail or erode norms and the
landscape in such way it is equivalent
to representation of
the landscape itself and the constraints
that constitute this landscape
and the way the flow of landscape
reconfigures the landscape so what I did
here is to basically
Prime theorem of Creative Evolution this
of a set of constraints well of a
structural landscape
uh on the way individual agents act to
understand and act within this landscape
I have a sense in which constant
observation and cognition about physical
here a social reality but still physical
in a sense that it exists in a physical
world
um
how this landscape can be created by
something that is cognitive and this
basic ontology if I am correct here is
something we can mathematize I hope so
and that we can frame as a basic theory
of well the individuation of new
physical possibilities ER creation ie
uh credit to this graph is given to
nabernacle
and
what is of importance here is The
Duality between two representation uh
two perspective the perspective of agent
that basically enact circular social
cultural constraints that the experience
has
a physical fact as a reality they cannot
go beyond or Escape or maybe a fact in
Brute Force that's possibility but not
Escape
and the perspective of a set of
constraints that indigenously unfolds in
a way that is creative
and that is a formal intuition I plan to
build on
and I can
say something a bit more specific about
how it works by analogy to differentiate
principle
and the allographic principle
basically a creation operator
in my opinion I could argue for that I
will not do this in detail right now
it's something that goes for a space of
it's not actually a space of physical
possibilities it's a space of
potentialities it does not have possible
States and impossible states it is just
the statement that something is possible
it is very close to what Greeks call
chaos
so you have such a space of
possibilities and from the space unfolds
a pair of an individual observable which
is called efr environment and an agent
that is capable to observe this survival
and the agent is also capable to
maintain uh boundary between itself and
the observable or basically types
available to stay existing as I'm
survival to be observed
um
and from this I think
that some mathematical operator that
does this basic flow is capable to
describe the construction of physical
spaces as they are the unfolding uh
strictly strictly no metaphorically a
physical structure as
basically the
yes the emergence the co-construction
the integration as you will of uh well
invigorated observable States and
observer that is capable to see the
state and biasing these states
maintaining whatever worked as an
integrated space of possibilities before
as a well-integrated boundary between
itself and the system
let us think for example of a piece of
paper
I an agent can basically write things on
it and by writing things on it I create
new physical apps available which is the
content of what I've written and the
facts I write on it and or read it makes
a piece of paper not
a piece of paper but a boundary between
myself and a semiotic space where the
writing occurs
this is the basic Dynamic that's
must be framed for us to understand
cognitive meaning
and that if we framed in such way could
work to describe the construction of the
species X nilo because literally you do
not need physical possibilities to be a
thing for B to exist it is the point of
this presentation you don't need a space
of possibilities to pre-exist
the in the duration of the agent and
environment
this is why it is relevant and this is
why it is hard to formulate and given an
operator with this property we can
pretty much work it back on the
foundation of physics and see what
happens
so have a physics of creation
let us
tie the threads of this presentation I
will
formulate three take-home messages
first
we have something that is called the fep
that is now framed that is mainly framed
as a Bayesian mechanics as informational
enrichment of the mucosystem theory but
that can also be framed as something in
Quantum information Theory
it says that agents actively infer
states of meaning through their
engagement with the environment in a way
that maintains their structure
this gives us a formal background
um
the quantum frame it on the sorry
Quantum framing of its gives us a very
very tentative and hard to say
I would not say ill-specified but
very few specified it's it does not does
not have a lot of detail so it gives us
a very not detailed background uh for
the study of how cognitive meaning
um underwrites the construction of
physical spaces
but because it is very attract and not
very specified
we have related in a much stronger way
to the classical formulation of the FTP
where the internal flow of the agent and
the synchronization manifolds that
emerge from the interaction
of a very specific topology of a
specific very specific geometry and can
be equipped with meaning about the
underlying physical structure
second
we have to admit that past materialism
is a thing
we have to admit that there is something
wrong in how we view science
let us uh quote Einstein if without in
any white disability system we can
predict with certainty the value of a
physical quantity then there exists and
the amount of reality corresponding to
that quantity by this account nothing is
real which is a very big problem
a very bad position to hold
and we have in some sense to account
a faulty role observation in creating
Well mutating Physical States not only
for quantum physics not only for
cognitive science but for everything in
between
which is in some sense entail by quantum
physics in the same some sense and tail
by cognitive sense so I don't think it
is a very big deal to say that but I
think it will be taken as such
and
the statement I want to make is that not
only doing away with this brand of
realism is compatible with naturalistic
damage with science
but it's also necessary
because for naturalistic science to be a
thing I have to represent myself
representing
as
there is something metaphysical that
comes to play is there as attacking
myself as a detached non-physical
describer of the world or by postulating
some kind of god-like pre-existing
structure that I just happened to
stumbled upon you will have something
that is beyond physics in some sense if
you don't do away with physical with
this brand of centrifugalism and
um it has been said to me that it is not
a new view no it is not it has been
framed as a criticism of the national
Fatman thing in itself by a Liberties
philosopher about three million years
ago
and
the fact is not new is not
really a problem in my opinion we should
go with things that seem true whether or
not
they are exciting and novel and the fact
that we can have a cosmology without
uh practice in nature and
other people do not find any problem
with it should be a sign that maybe our
insistence that no there are things in
themselves is not well motivated
and finally
um
what I propose here
beyond the physical considerations and a
discussion of what some piece of math do
is very very very very basic not draft
but
drawing of physical creation that holds
in two movements the first is
abstractly the invitation of something
from nothing of all the word cows
um given a space of undefined
possibilities B uh you have in iteration
of an observable that is well defined
and of an agent whose observation of e
also invigorates a boundary
so we have this kind of
framing
that
codes work as a handle on how to write
the space Construction
it does have a very strong category 30
called filler from the way basically the
content of B is not what's at stake this
diagram is pretty much agnostic
concerning what B is and is not and it
must be because it underwrites the
becoming of the
um
and there is a lot of work
if I want the fixed operation to be a
thing and framing properly what kind of
mathematical operator
basically follow the flow of this
diagram and what those mathematical
operators do and the kind of physics
like Candlelight but for this I have a
constraint case I have decays of how
humans collaborate to build and recreate
social norms because it is a case of
creation like it is pretty much the
single case of creation I could convince
anyone is a thing there is money because
we believe there is money and it works
as we believe it works because we
believe it works this way it is very
true statement to say that Norms
constrain us
because we believe in norms
and The Duality it affords between the
representation of single agents trying
to understand and act within a social
world and the flow the increasing flow
that is created by the social
constraints and that recreate social
constraints
they just practice specific it's much
more specific than
the vague operator I haven't left and I
know this operator must represent that
so it gives basically some level of grip
at this entity level on how the fixed up
creation would work
and they would work by describing the
unfolding of physical structure as the
construction within physics of meaning
and or constraints over what is
observable by vivanagerty Observers
and uh yeah pretty much we have to work
from there because
um
I do not think there is there is no
self-consistent in the sense I
introduced earlier there is no
self-consistent Theory of physics if we
don't do that so let's do that
um this work again is uh to some extent
my work to some extent the collective
work of keros
which is basically
um
it is past particular battery that works
towards uh an active sense and acting
naturalism a sense that his naturalist
in the sense that it plays The Observer
within the world and works within
well-defined causal ontology rather than
less well-defined laws and Abstract
principles
and it tries to do so in a way that
enables people was in humans
to understand their reality to basically
use this knowledge about how the world
Works to constrain their own behavior
and navigate the world especially given
well the recommendation of straw
constraints that will
we expect and be at play in the coming
decades so I strongly suggest you take a
look to our website and our general line
of work and consider if you want to talk
to us or join us the QR code is I
believe a link to our website
so uh thanks to Maxwell thanks to
Danielle thanks to Alexi thanks to Jonah
thanks to pretty much everyone who
helped me write this and think it
through it was big work
uh so I will run through this slide if
someone wants to read them in the video
and now we can go uh toward the
discussion
excellent thank you
thank you
Alexian Maxwell welcome back if you want
to join and please either of you
provide a
first statement or any set of questions
however you want to continue just go for
it
you know what give me five minutes I
will uh try to
um destroy my heads
so shots but don't expect me to
okay
well do you want to share your
perspective on the project things that
Avo would be familiar with while you're
here
uh yeah uh I Can Begin I guess
um yeah so I worked on the metaphysical
ontological path and yeah to me I will
give it a good uh
good presentation yeah it was really
nice to see it's framed into the horror
um
way of talking about
everything
like linking it to FTP and then to other
stuff
so yeah the
um so the point of the if I can share a
bit more about uh the metaphysics of the
ontology
um the idea was to create a an ontology
that is naturalist and as fep seems to
be really naturalist then I wanted like
to make it work together
at first it was only in my own
my own field that I developed this
Anthology and then are very said to me
that it was really linked together
so that's what what we try to do here
yeah
what does that look like how are you
evaluating
what a metaphysic is or how you know
when you found the right one or an
incompatible one
yeah so the basic question
was about the question of what exists
more generally so that was my my anger
of attack if it's a thing in English
yeah so
um there are many discussions about what
there is in philosophy
mainly in the 20th century due to Crime
I think it is popular in general in the
culture of science
um so I followed these debates on what
there is and
pretty much there are a lot of views
about what there is and what there is
not so
I was a bit how to say that disturbed by
the fact that there are things that are
not
um and I wanted to give it a try to
try to talk about what seems not to be
and to make it exist in some way and
so um how to say that better like
generally what doesn't exist is linked
to Consciousness like
Pegasus or
let's say stupid sentences such as the
round square copula of the clay College
um
uh something else such as I don't know
some weird not really mathematical
entities and I was like okay so
uh I agree that they do not work but at
least we are talking about them
so can't we just say they exist in some
way and then I went into social ontology
uh and I found that we can call them
social artifacts
and then I was a bit relieved with this
view so I tried to to make it work with
also
phenomenality or cognitive or personal
experience Human Experience because
being a social artifact doesn't make it
all so yeah then I
I just tried to make it work between
ontology social Anthology and cognitive
ontology
and
yeah that's it and also yeah so uh
something else Avail talked about the
self-referential inconsistency so it's a
debate uh
uh I've found by
by working on ontology and I was really
into it the fact that a theory is
inconsistent if it doesn't apply to
itself
and and I found some articles about it
which were against naturalism that's one
kind of naturalism only so it was mostly
uh eliminationism and I saw that the
people who were working on that they
didn't know about a lot of naturalism
and as I I work with Kairos and in my
history uh I found that there are many
kinds of natural disease so I saw that
the the argument doesn't work with other
kinds of naturalism such as the
the one that is developed here yeah
I hope it's clear
yep
I'll ask one question on this topic from
the chat and then feel free to take it
in any direction or Maxwell So Adam
rostowski in the chat asked
thanks Apple question maybe for Alexi
what if State space is considered
theoretical ideology rather than causal
ontology it's presupposition would then
not be a threat to ontological
consistency
so what if State space is considered
theoretical ideology rather than causal
ontology maybe just unpack the question
and then give a thought
yeah I will write it now in order to
reflect on it
perhaps I will just a direct question
what are the state spaces that you're
concerned with
how would you characterize what they are
by construction test spaces there are
spaces of postulated physical
possibilities
the other particular I do not understand
what the inertia of Neurology how it
works here
um
you have
it's pretty trivial that what we usually
call ideology will Define what a person
or political system or institution is
capable slash interested
uh in seeing
it is um it is a topic of
Scott single States
uh
foundational let's say work of federal
case anthropology that books at
basically how
um
whenever States try to do things uh are
very clearly usually for the population
their main concern in effect is to build
the capability of control and usually
they do so by
cutting through complexity aggressively
a very basic instance of that is
scientific forestry that is
I can say it is indeed for a stream
um the idea was that partially did war
robots loads of them we also needed to
be able to predict how many more modes
more boats they would build on a given
um
time frame so I need to know how many
compatible trees they had but you don't
have robot compatible trees and not
worry about multiple trees you have
trees or different size different ages
um different sounds so if you just
continue trees even with a well-defined
measure you would not really know how
many trees you have so they just raised
for rest and planted homogeneous patch
of given species at a given time with
even soil so they knew that once I knew
they had a
64 uh I don't know what trees there are
I actually know what trees they are I
don't know it's totally in English so
when they had a
I will it's not Oak but I will say Oak
to say something uh when they knew they
had a 64 uh 30 years old well that's 64.
uh
30 I did say 30. so that's a 30 30 is
Oaks and that's it they can cut the
trees and they know exactly what they
can do with it
um so this is a way in which
what something we could account as
ideology so the notion that we should be
able to control blah blah blah blah it's
um basically construct physical reality
in very concrete sense because the
country like plant other trees that fit
their expectation it is a form of Niche
construction it is a form of um
how you call that cognitive accession in
the sense that the loads like what needs
to account for
our trees are they
just
upload it onto the environment by making
trees actually all the same
and it is a form of meaning projection
by other stuff winning which is
that they need to count trees that are
barboats compatible and they project it
onto by
how actual forests are organized
[Music]
um
but and this is uh these those are
physical possibilities as much better
State those are set spaces we have a
state space that was very complex with a
lot of possible trees possible species
possible size that is a
um brought down to how many trees I have
and
it is uh
could you repeat the question word for
word please because it was not clear to
me how audition of physiology intervened
what if State space is considered
theoretical ideology rather than causal
ontology it's presupposition would then
not be a threat to ontological
consistency
the causal
yes okay
it precedes a space it is the ontology
of uh creation slash constraints that I
have um waved that
um somewhat impressively at the moment
uh set space uh R I think I think I will
be able to demonstrate it but I counted
the moment they express the point of
view of an agent so I imagine that this
is what is meant to be introduced by uh
a logical Theory theoretical ideology
and um
I do not think State space are a threat
to ontology I think ontologies that
consider stat spaces as fundamental are
float ontology is fine
thank you Avo Alexi feel free to chime
in and then Maxwell if you want to add
anything
yeah
um so I think I will join available on
the
documentary
um also I would like to say that
um if we take quiet division of ideology
if I will not explain this now that well
yeah so the idea I think is that the
concepts are Auto and not fundamental
stuff that's what I think it is implied
by ideology here
um so what I'd say is that
um
you give the value of being an ideology
a consolantology depending of your your
goal and your criteria
but at least minimally you're the stuff
you're talking about it is that's the
the fundamental stuff uh that are that I
would say yeah so even though it is
ideological even though it is
instrumental let's say minimality is
something and it has consequences on the
world and that's what I think I've ever
said with the uh nicheconstruction
of social time it is didn't really say
that in these words but yeah even though
your IDs are let's say stupid or upset
and the and people appear to hear you
then your ideas they are in the world
and they do something
yeah so
I hope I insert like if not then I can
see the questions
[Music]
thank you
Maxwell do you want to add something or
I don't currently have anything burning
to say uh I I will I think this is the
uh well this is the nth iteration of our
discussions around this
um I mean as always I think you did a
great job presenting what I think is uh
you know a genuine issue uh
and I mean I I've just been rehearsing
the same
um you know appeals to multi-scalarity
um I mean I I find it interesting uh
that you uh would speak uh an answer to
the these uh issues in Quantum fep
um precisely because of its scale-free
nature so you know you can't appeal to a
space-time background when speaking in
uh the quantum fep formulation so I
think uh that in my mind that makes
things
um potentially more difficult I see why
you would want to do that because of the
focus on
um you know the the definition of an
observation as a physical interaction
I guess I'm my uh my kind of uh
overarching question is whether the
multi-scalarity of classical fep helps
at all uh in the sense that we described
uh before so you have a set of
observables some of them change too fast
to really like disclose or allow us to
track reliably some phenomenon behind
the blanket others do in the latter case
we talked about states in the former we
talk about random fluctuations so I
suspect that you know the the kind of
definitional uh uh discussions like uh
by which I mean like you know
definitions of States like these kind of
foundational issues that arise uh In
classical fep might be helpful
hereabouts uh I also suspect that you'll
disagree with me so I'm looking forward
to hearing your thoughts
so um
basically uh you have a
the distinction is clear between us
at least as you friendly problem you
seem to be realist about the physical
possibilities about spaces which I'm not
I have another month for non-realism
which is a self control what ontological
consistency and determinants of
self-constituency and selfless
resistancy that brings us to say that
you can't have preemptive spaces in
which uh to frame in which to classify
have physical observables that somehow
pre-exist physics nature the process
that are within it
so that is one theoretical arguments the
question is then can I demonstrate
conclusively that you do not have
physical survivals before observation
but State spaces do in fact reduce the
perspective of server and basically if I
can demonstrate it the the debate is
over
um
until then you have
you can basically uh hold you can hold
structuralism but
you have to account uh of how thing
exists if they are not fundamental I
think uh multiscal fpp can do that so
it's not a critical problem for you
everything holds on the formal
demonstration that we do not in fact
have uh set spaces
as a prompted physical effects
well I'm just I wouldn't push a little
bit back against your realism versus
anti-realism uh distinction here I'm
really just talking about uh well I'm
really just talking about like at the
level of the formalism you start with
some of the observables which seems to
be what you are also uh staying and then
you uh can talk about the way that those
observables are related to uh some other
things which may be latent all of that
is a formal statement as far as I'm
concerned and like it is useful whether
or not it maps in some kind of
fundamental realist ontology sense I I
guess like if if there is a there is a
kind of transcendental overtone to what
I'm saying in the sense that I I you
know we've argued in print in this on
the map territory fallacy fallacy paper
that the um the fep theoretic maths and
you know the related cluster of
principles unitarity maximum entropy and
so forth provide ultimate constraints on
any model building exercise just full
stop so like again that that doesn't
presuppose any realism about what maps
map onto it's really just a statement
about like the construction and maybe
the process of constructing
um
you're corrected since I wasn't it was
uh
uh attributing
I I don't know how to say it's English
it was not accurate to frame you as a
realist about spaces it was correct
however to frame you as an
instrumentalist which I refuse to be uh
because of naturalism basically I
consider it necessary to frame causal
ontologies that map onto reality
properly
as fine grantly as we can and to do that
we have to include basically the
Constitutional relation
and this is when everything becomes
complicated because you can't say if
there are such physical possibilities
then this occurs you can't use that
language because
by doing that you frame physical
possibilities as something that is
abstracted from the underlying physical
reality you
um decouple the formal from the actual
and
I think whatever ontology we use must be
virtualities but must corresponds
sexually to what drives reality so I
have a it is the contrary it is a i who
is the realist but the constraint I was
going to say
maybe uh maybe actually the so I guess
you know basically this clarifies
I go for ontology that is consistent in
the since I friend and the constraint
over that are much much much much
stronger than the constraint of our
instrumentalists ontology that just yeah
we say interesting things
which is not actually easy it's just
much more easy
but suppose we started from the
assumption that we don't have to have a
strong position on the reality of State
spaces uh
does that affect your argument at all so
you know if I were to say like I I just
as the practitioner of science start
from my observables you can be a radical
phenomenologist from this point of view
if you want you're just starting from
your observables and then working out
like what resists your manipulations or
interactions
um yeah does that in your View kind of
allow us to move around asking the
questions
you can move around with oh about the
fix of creation no
um move around yes understand some
things with creative meaning yes you
have a fep grounds cognitive meaning in
clinical center it's huge deal
um
what's it
what it does not is afford the
ontological consistent
Theory of physics and the difference
between us is not what we hold the fep
to do I think we are both
instrumentalists
um
you as a realist
but
the difference is that I see an
affordance to build a much stronger
self-consistent Physical Therapy that
draws elements and the general
Philosophy from the fvp the philosophy
of practice in France basically
[Music]
um
excuse me I push in this direction
because I think the goal is variable
it is ultimately an ethical call if you
do not agree that the goal is variable
you should not agree that it is useful
to push it I do not have ultimately
unsure that
so maybe uh there is a kind of Conti
intake
um here because I I I mean I think in
the at least in the history of
philosophy this uh split between realism
and anti-realism or instrumentalism I
mean uh like I think it's perhaps overly
simplistic as a description of the
potential options uh there you know
there is a whole kantian line of
thinking uh that talks about uh
you know something intermediate in some
sense
um so you know
yeah I don't know uh just a thought
so um I couldn't liberate is uh Adam in
the room a damn if you're in the room uh
Houston shots
I agree that
not in the room but I can read another
question whenever you're done I'll read
another question from the chat
yeah but I was going to say something
which is that I agree that the basically
is the distinction between her
instrumentalism and
unrealism must be dissolved because both
none of them are liturgically consistent
both suppose representation relation
that is outside the world and the
question is whether
the words as a formal construct
correspond to the reality as a
structural thing and there's not a
concerned question to ask the all of the
things are in the world we have to have
a theory of how things are true or not
that are false for the statements we
have about the world to be in the world
because they are
um
and so from
once you agree that uh
ontological constances something to have
a lot of the distinction we have in
Western philosophy will be dissolved
which makes communication complicated of
course
Maxwell you want a closing thought on
that or I'll ask the next question
um you can ask the next question I think
that that brings us uh nicely to uh yeah
this is from Alex Kiefer
so Alex wrote I love the positive story
in this paper insofar as I understand it
which I'm still working on and the idea
of treating even such things as state
spaces and scientific reps as amenable
to physical descriptions
but to bounce off what Maxwell is saying
I'm not sure I see the Deep critique of
thing in itself realism here
probably depends what one means by that
I tend to think of the strictly
incoherent kantian idea of something
unknowable behind phenomena so why is
treating state-space creation as part of
phenomena at odds with that
just to pick up on that I think um you
know we you don't need to be a strong
realist uh you can just believe that you
know you are more or less getting it
right and the the semantics that we've
proposed uh you know that uses active
inference and the free energy principle
is a kind of uh formal basis but
precisely uses the fact that you know
you have a certain perspective you have
certain beliefs and your beliefs are
going to be more or less wrong uh and
that the the prediction error or the
free energy is precisely what like what
you need to uh the kind of minimal
ingredient that you need to hook you
into a situation enough to uh you know
be doing something
you know pragmatic that you might call
truth-telling
um I think the uh yeah that that's
really all you need from a formal point
of view is just the ability to be wrong
um and to change your mind in light of
new evidence
so my claim is not that everything in
physics is false and
um formal statement about
postulated possibilities of no epistemic
value or trivial epistemic value
my claim is that
those representation as any
representation are
um relational they write two objects
and the truth value or value in a sense
that we have to give the meaning we have
to give to that
if we are to give anything at all it
must be grounded in the study of
physical Dynamics that's underlying
their margins
if we are to have again an ontologic
consistent Theory we could just say that
sense is this course that is not
entirely false and say things that are
not entirely false I could do that
uh
again the notion that
series physical this course must be
anthologically consistent
is ultimately a sequel like it is a
segment on what you should and should
not do I can say that it is better
because x y z you can say that XYZ are
not meaningful targets to have and that
whatever we do is okay essentially or
maybe it's better than a XYZ
uh but the notion that I am
I do not critiques that spaces but at
least it's an open point I have to find
as a Critic to
for it to resonate but the point is that
species are rational property
and that to study this uh Russian
rationality it reframes the entirety of
physics its epistemology it's ontology
it's cosmology and
if you look at
the flow of this Theory it's not
pure obstruction eternalize
social Evolution so evolution is Agent
predicting meaning as norms and then the
normal swing that things
it is something that is very
basic for us to understand how solar
system evolve and yet there is no such
Theory there is no theory of social
Evolution that do not presuppose this
variation and Abstract away and in form
of structure and Metabolism it simply
does not exist
so the non-existence of naturalistic
theory of revolution is maybe a pretty
big problem for a purely predictive uh
pragmatic value standpoint
from a more abstracting point
we don't have a current cosmology we
don't have
an explanation for why why there are
things and why the things that are look
like what they are so physically we just
have to postulate that stats by space
time is such and such for physics of
Excellence
which is a problem we can't have
a physical therapy that is that stands
only on
the fact that its statement does not
give rise to obvious problems
we have to have something beyond the
statement we have to have some way to
account for how this statement became
true
and it is a pretty basic point to make
in Psychology biology sociology we can
just say things are such and such we
have to say how they become such and
such and why they become subject search
which is uh nothing in evolution nothing
biology makes like
nothing in biology makes sense accepting
light solution
and it is because those are systems that
are I don't like theological let's say
leonami color those are still not
organized that are coherent that work in
a specific way and
so we have to
cannot just say they do X we have to say
how and why they do X and this
epistemology has not
[Music]
has not permeated physics basically
because of the belief of physicists in a
platonic truth of symmetries or
formalism or symmetric uh I have a
question uh for you uh well
um
so I'm thinking about this in terms of
the direction of travel of our research
on the free energy principle uh which I
mean there are two main components to uh
that we could discuss that are relevant
here the first is a move from
state-based to uh path based or past
integral formulations
where what what what's at stake is
precisely probability density functions
not over individual states but over
trajectories entire trajectories of the
system where like what what your
generative model or lagrangian is
describing is the probability of some
specific history
um so this kind of yeah intrinsically
historical formalization
um and on the other hand uh as a kind of
second uh main direction of travel uh
really formalizing these kind of three
nested scales of inference where you
have uh inference over uh State factors
and individual states like you know
color and red green blue and so on
um inference over the parameters uh of
the model uh the characterize the
relations between uh States and
configurations of states and finally the
structure of the model which is really
like the uh the actual uh you know
relations and functionality of like what
is connected to what
um so one of the things that we're uh
you know working on is getting to uh the
mathematical foundations of these uh
basically mutually constraining scales
of inference uh so suppose you know you
had access to a path based description
of the free energy uh you know formalism
uh supplemented by a clear uh you know a
clear formulation of inference uh nested
within a parameter
optimization nested within structure
optimization you know the so in other
words like assuming that we solve
structure learning which is a big
assuming but you know if you granted
those two things would there be still
much of a problem you think from a
formal point of view if you could just
like move in the space of all possible
model structures and paths through
such spaces
would you not basically address what you
have in mind here
um yeah
so
um
three things first
integral it solves the issue of
preset meaning for biological systems
and the issue of well use of that
already
but it is not something like code on
here so it would not help with the issue
I've discussed
secondly structural learning the
question is how basically living things
project structure
if we have that
we would progress in a big way uh
Forest area of cognitive meaning and
agency
but
you will still operate within a given
space of possibilities you will have a
attraction slash contraction of the
state of possibles by the migrantry of
what the fep is it is it builds uh
manifold so the manifold like the thing
will evolve on the manifold where it
will evolve
um so some of this that space will
become trivial some of the dimension
will become trivial
um
foreign but and some things that would
not that do not really appear per see in
the set space will become relevant
so they will become part of the state
space as experienced by the agent but
the hard part is to account for how this
takes place
um as a students by the agent becomes
this at space per C how you have
uh
Matrix of 6 or 6
that serves as a bandarita to say and
how agents will basically
collaboratively build systems meaning
where they have alphabet and can
communicate long sentences using this
this grid
and
this is not in and of itself a question
of structural learning although
um
solving City learning wasn't able to
to have a lot of computational
experiments that would help greatly with
uh looking at the fine grain structure
the question is how you use
how you use mathematics
in a way
um well in a way of describes creation
this has the the construction set spaces
but that's what I'm suggesting space
that's what I'm suggesting when um so
the you know what what I'm talking about
is if if you could figure out when to
add a new node or connect or uh Edge to
your generative model like precisely
when is it appropriate to add a new
parameter when is it appropriate to say
oh these two parameters are connected to
that space in these proportions if you
had that worked out I I could see a kind
of straightforward resolution to what
you're talking about I'm not saying like
you know there is the system just
unfolds dynamically and occasionally you
know it's it learns new structure or
parameters which basically means like
you know the new degrees of freedom are
added to the system
you are again talking at the epistemic
level you can't describe a lot of things
um by basically looking at the Dynamics
and being smart about it
you don't you don't even need uh
advanced mathematics to do that
this statement we make is different let
us say that you have people that agree
that shells are an appropriate means of
exchange of our x y and z
uh then money becomes a thing it is a
thing that exists individually because
uh it has structural properties and
these properties drive observatables
through Dynamics
and
equally individually did not exist one
before
the question we ask is
how we account for an evolution within a
space that builds another space
and
we cannot just look at between the space
and declare how it has changed
it is not the problem we are posing
problem is how it's reason
mathematically something that occurs
within space that produce another space
that is the same but not the same
that is structurally
um similar that inherits from what
existed before but is different in
Collective aspect because this one thing
became
so what we have to have is the theory of
becoming basically
and
um
we can be very smart about modeling
things
without having a theory of becoming we
can be very precise in chemical
inference and very
efficient at seeing regime changes that
does not mean we have a self-consistent
theory of becoming creation space
construction correct what we like those
are two different problems and so one
may help the other greatly both may help
the other greatly because
um the thing we are looking at is the
same word looking at two very different
aspects of the thing
Maxwell want to add something or Alexa
on that no I'm gonna think about that
um thank you Emma
awesome yeah from the chat on that topic
Tom wrote a similar question Avila could
you elaborate more on how active could
be expanded to accommodate State space
creation assuming active is normative
about free energy minimization when
should an agent expand the state space
and Alex Kiefer also kind of uh added a
note it's appropriate to add a new
parameter when the model complexity
accuracy trade-off says so more
seriously isn't free energy measurable
across models or different state spaces
so it's almost like
there's the structure learning
meta cognition layer and it almost is
like can the Box be wrapped within the
Box
can it be possible to have a state space
that within its state space represents
itself and or to what extent do these
physical intermediates and their
Associated physics and metaphysics need
to come into play
for different systems and at what level
of generality
basically about this I'd subscribed to a
variant of consistent history
interpretation of quantum physics but
it's not quantum physics is just
something that has the kind of ethical
parties quantum physics has
um
well I did commit to Quantum information
several years so okay let us say it is a
in nature Quantum which is a bit trivial
because yes it has PCS in it which is
what being Quantum is but whatever
um
the
this is the most specific uh
mathematically
consistent way to presented from you
still see those slides yep EBA
EBA
e
um
and this is basically category Theory
because
um
this diagram as a property which is that
uh following the arrows basically change
what the space is
B begins as a neutral interface so a
space of possibilities
that in principle are for interaction
but it is not semantically loaded and
the fact that you have the integration
of e the observatables and a I from data
as an agent but it would rather be
agentive capabilities or constraints
that enable observation of E
so um
this does not conserve the property of B
Because B becomes equipped with a
semantics
so real theories that look at spaces
without looking at what is in spaces
those are category series
and those are the most abstract field of
mathematics as far as I know and I
do not afford uh semantically loaded
things like Furniture is a measure of
not only it entails the states but it
also entails a measure of States I think
the basic mathematical structure we need
to represent that
is much more basic than any other things
and any energy measure will break down
much before we get there
but
but we are that is more expensively
loaded is this The Duality between the
experience of
struggle to landscape by agents and the
introduce flow that is directed by the
landscape and reconstructed landscape
so
um
the question was what was the question
could you repeat it word forward Daniel
it was just about the uh
normativity around model selection and
whether modeling State spaces could or
would require
[Music]
artifact
the innovativity
um is uh
there it is in this representation of
the problem uh I have a small agent that
represents uh circular landscape and
acts within it and I can't just claim
okay there is that space there is a
Flawless at space I can defend for
energy Resurgence minimize strategy
and then this is where structural
learning intervenes basically because
those agents will try to understand the
ones they do not experience the world
directly they will infer the world in a
way that is robust and competent but
they can
make up new things they can fail to
understand they can cheat they can erode
the structure of the landscape that is
collectively enacted in many ways and
this again is dual to something that is
the uh chemical it's not dynamical
actually I do not know what it is it
doesn't work the uh unfolding of uh the
structure of the landscape under its own
Sound flow that again is not dynamical
because it's not what we call sensory
size
so we described what you're talking
about in terms of Niche Construction
yeah so uh in human systems I thought
yeah we had a Carl and I had an
interesting discussion about this a few
weeks ago and uh yeah I think what what
really distinguishes human systems from
non-human systems is the degree to which
the active inference Loop is mediated by
uh what would otherwise be internal
States but that end up having this kind
of ambiguous function of yeah they're
environmental that they they encode the
material aspects of some normative
practice uh or some they store some
information uh about what you're doing
like a like a a Blackboard for instance
or or these slides that we're all
looking at and you know in some sense
encode the the thought or aspects of the
thought that you're trying to
communicate
um so the
yeah maybe a lot of the problem here can
be finessed by noting that it's not just
about agents interacting with each other
there is a kind of common store of you
know or traces you know like a kind of
material thing that we all have in
common yeah
[Music]
you have a common uh collective in
action of a given structure to landscape
because humans are such that then they
synchronize in a robust and sponsored
loaded way and that Circle the landscape
it does not exist
it is not something that pre-exists the
fact that agents do that agents infer
properties and then enact them
and this make it an open landscape
and the normativity of the fep affords
um
probably a computational experiment
design that help us see how such
landscape unfolds and look at Material
Theory where the agent is absent where
it is landscape that produce landscape
and once we have that we have a theory
of creation it is what the theory of
creation is
so so what you're saying is if we had a
theory where the agent was able to like
expand its state space through structure
and parameter learning in particular
then we would have what you're looking
for am I misunderstanding
uh yes but I'm not sure that we agree
that we're aligned on the constraints of
these segments entails
because we
the goal is not to understand how the
agent engage with personal environments
it is to abstract
if we get uh to the Target we can
abstract entirely the agent in what they
think and just look at constraints and
how they informed I went to light on the
constraint technology because we do not
have it was not the place for that but
we need to look at specifically
constraints over what is observable and
how they are invigorated and how they
produce other constraints etc etc we
have to get back at foreign
I mean you're talking about the same
thing so but the formulation uh that is
uh taken in uh physics Often by belief
is DST it entails uh promptive space and
this is what needs to be
um to address the problem I want to
address this is why to have to be a
overcome
and this
is likely possible given a constraints
and trick ontology so ontology where do
not have possibilities then constraints
about the possibilities but constraints
then possibilities afforded by
constraints
and I do know what I'm saying is that
those two stories are the same story uh
that's a Bayesian mechanics cells that
that yeah it is from within DST
uh but they're both from DST what the I
mean so a uh free energy principle
theoretic model of the belief the
updating of a particle in a system is is
in the strong sense of like is dual to
you if I have one I have the other right
is uh a maximum entropy dynamical
systems model of uh the whole system as
in the whole system of particles and
environment to which it's coupled and
all of that sensory motor like that
that's okay that's the cool thing it's
the the the the fep is the canonically
optimal dynamical systems model uh it's
maximum entropy in the sense that you
know it uh is the it makes the least
assumptions given your current state of
knowledge about the system you know
it's James uh James as in you know j a y
and yes it's Jane's optimal in the
parlance of
daltonville uh yes so if you have a
constraints model you also have an fep
model and vice versa if you work it out
from the perspective of the FTP you can
map back onto a constraint but
definitionally
constraint model with no reference
whatsoever to the micro System Theory or
pre-existing species so yes I agree you
absolved the problem
but the paper which referred to frames
it within DST
which is
those that we need to get Beyond to
solve this specific problem again I did
not mean to say basically you have a you
have uh framed this equivalence
I think
up to details let us have two details I
would need to think about it actually
um but uh with hypothesis that are
precisely those that I want to use the
equivalence to overcome
you know constraints don't get you out
of the problem that you were posing
originally either like both no in you
just you have another kind of layer of
you know pre-given
is not we have to characterize
constraints it is that we have to have
an ontology of constraints so much
medical constructs that use this
constraints with no reference to
anything else just constraints
questions I don't know but if we have
that in the sense while conserving the
sense that these are given by Mercy
Moreno and while leveraging the
equivalence between constraints and
belief that well meaning belief whatever
that is derived we have one but it is
not something that has been done because
fep is friend within uh well one eiffp
vfcp is a friend within DST which press
release States and qfvp is
one does not specify what buildups
library just specify that there are
observables that we can make survivals
but we can't solve this within DST or
within a pure abstract Quantum function
series is not afforded by the structure
of these theories once because it states
the other principles of servers we have
to show how those
are become integrated
and the only way forward that I see is a
constraint ontology
so right so what I'm saying is this is
mathematically speaking if you're
talking about constraints then there is
a in the end it's probably functorial I
mean you know there is a rigorous and
systematic mapping from what you're
talking about to what the FTP is already
saying
um that's that's really yeah I mean that
that's that's really what The Duality is
saying like yeah uh maximizing your
entropy with respect to some set of
constraints is dual to minimizing your
free energy with respect to some model
it's the same thing if you have one you
always have the other
if uh how would you frame the notion of
a constraint in your sense of Monsieur
montervier and Moreno with no reference
to either GST or in related States well
I mean in these reaction networks that
they're mapping they are implicitly
using some kind of space
production networks it is a another line
of work
right but like I'm just saying that
there is a similar kind of like
individuation of things that's going on
when you map out like some kind of
constrained uh schematic in in that
sense like yeah the uh the point that
you're making sort of like
grandfathers both here which is okay but
how do you you know write down a state
space model at all and how do they how
do you grow them in particular
um but I guess I'm just saying like yeah
constraints are just the subject to this
as to the extent that the fep is subject
to your criticism the constraint stuff
is also for the same or dual reasons
like if you just inverted all of the
arrows in your reasoning you would also
be able to apply this to the constraint
stuff equally like that's not an exit
to what you're pointing out but I guess
my my complimentation if you think there
is a uh if you think moving to a
constraint ontology helps us then that's
interesting because any like constraint
mapping is also dual to an fep theoretic
model uh so maybe the fep can be used
like very directly just based on the way
that you're like if you solve the
problem in terms of constraints you
could flip it back it doesn't really uh
and it I don't know if you're stuck
along the way then you can flip it at
that point and think okay well does
looking at does looking at it from this
like do I want to look at
self-organization from the perspective
of the selves that are self-organizing
are from the perspective of organization
and you know the maximization of entropy
and all that stuff I guess
so if you're arguing that the FTP treats
an entire different people naturally
different problem this is not of your
hold it is a viewer opposed specifically
I do agree that physics of and by belief
derives within the St rigorous relation
between basically what are the two sides
of this up to details
um what I am saying is framing as a goal
the fact to leverage that other way to
um
of
space construction and I also claim that
this would be essentially equivalent uh
to build a
self-consistent and automatically
consistent
um
constraint Anthology for uh for for that
for this diagram
um I'm not sure what you're going to get
because it is an ambiguous that your
research has of noise framed within DST
which precipices states which the
constraint topology would not and it is
indigo that he is very relevant because
it's as you said entails one Duality at
least in one specific case which is list
of DST that is uh the key problem to
address so I think you wait you may be
combining two issues in this worry I
mean so that there is the worry of like
new States arising
and there's the worry of using
dates at all so I mean I think
so
yeah so it's the problem is not really
that you know dynamical systems theory
assumes States it's just the static nest
of the or the you know the
pre-determinedness or the priests best
defiantness okay so yeah so
specifically there is a very fruitful
Way Forward I think to address a lot of
them
my uh my proposal is a state space
construction not the state space
stationism to get uh uh right I need B
to begin with I need physical things to
be there well to have a actually
self-consensory you would need this to
work from uh X nilo to get something
from nothing
but it is not the issue attend here the
issue at hand here is how existing
things can unfold create whatever
meaning States so it is not the notion
of states that is the problem the
problem is uh the fact that we do not
have a theory of how states are created
and we cannot frame it exclusively from
uh mathematical survey that by
construction precipose is a space of
possibilities
from this Theory to generalize it to the
space construction which is what I'm
proposing so but what about the
renormalization group so if you start
really from the idea that you just have
you know observations and they uh you
know have a scale of noise associated
with them
um yeah you can I think I mean there are
principled you know physics the kind of
ways of bootstrapping something kind of
saying well you know some stuff changes
so fast relative to my reference scale
that it basically averages out and just
contributes kind of random fluctuations
to what I'm observing
and you look at basically why to
personalize it to look at relevant
scales but
maybe it would be afforded to have a
hospitalism but it does not entail it
does not know the other password realism
it is a
model of how complex things complex
Dynamic unfold
so it is relevant it is not what I'm
pointing at
right
as we come near the end for each of us
maybe you can spend the most time at
Apple but for each of us what are our
next steps
what cognitive counterfactuals and
physical embodiments
are going to be shaped by this work and
discussion
maybe we can have non-avail go first
and then you can have the last word
sound good
okay well personally I'm very excited to
work on the category Theory this year
learning about the recent uh
dissertation of uh Toby Smith
also I think it's interesting to bring
in that Niche modification
active inference
variation ecology a lot of the work that
as Maxwell brought up earlier had been
framed within a multi-scale setting
bringing some of these new developments
over the last one or two years like the
path-based formalization renormalization
group environmental process uh
generative process generative model
symmetries weak Markov blankets there's
just many new Concepts and toolkits on
the table today
in 2023 then I think there were one or
two or three years ago
so it's been a super interesting
discussion and it brings a lot of topics
to
our attention that
I expect will be able to produce her
uncertainty about a lot in the coming
year
and I'll pass to Alexi then Maxwell and
then Apple
the opposite it would be more consistent
because Alexi and I work directly
together in Kairos okay Maxwell
um well I mean Daniel I would I would
Echo your overall uh assessment I share
your enthusiasm for where like
everything is at right now I think we're
poised for some very exciting work and a
lot of very uh interesting stuff has
happened over the short term uh in terms
of what others presented um I think uh
you know uh in addition to what you were
describing one of the things I want to
uh like work out this year is really um
the philosophy of the free energy
principle
or Bayesian mechanics I think uh up
until recently what what most everyone
has been doing myself included was just
coming at this thing from whatever you
know disciplinary background
we had access to in trying to just make
sense of it but uh I think that has made
us kind of blind to
some of the and everyone has kind of
their blind spots you know all of these
so-called interpretations of the fep
signal to me that there's there's
actually yeah there's there's
philosophical work to be done to kind of
understand uh Jules Hedges put it nicely
on Twitter I think he said that he's
become convinced of two things first the
fep is true in the sense that it's quote
unquote the right way to do it and
second that it's a lot more like boring
than all the hype suggests in the sense
that it's yeah it just follows from the
way that a bunch of physics hooks up
it's very very fundamental and important
but like yeah I mean um there are it
it's it's part of the kind of core
package now and there are new exciting
Horizons of like unknown that you know
more more to the the point is the the
there's there's like a a kind of core
philosophy to the fep that remains to be
uh developed so for example The Duality
between the principle of Maximum and
should be uh which you know implements a
form of like Occam's razor in some sense
and the free energy principle I think is
kind of deep and that we've only started
to think about you know the implications
that happened Chris fields's group has
been suggesting that there's a similar
Duality between the fep and uh unitarity
or the conservation of classical
information in
um yeah Quantum information Theory so uh
that's very exciting sorry for talking
so long
awesome exciting times indeed
all right Alexi and aval with the final
words
yeah so uh I will be shot so I'm really
excited about how these debates will
move the lines in theoretical but also
practical philosophy and on our direct
perception of staphy life in general to
be a bit fraud uh also I hope that part
of this will
um
make like I hope this will make the
difference in metaphysics and Anthology
and philosophy
and methodontology also and naturalism
of course as it seems to do in active
Insurance lab and Kairos
so we are three things we need to do to
um settle the dust on the ornament I
generated there the first is to
formalize much better segment and
ontological consistency and pastoralism
both need to be
very clear
in their reach and entailments this is
something we'll do with uh Alexi mainly
and possibly Auto Group members
uh
something that we need to do is to put a
lot of work in working out what this
basis mean I do not know I can tell you
that it is essentially correct I'm
pretty confident that's essentially
correct but I have no idea whatsoever
what it means click which is pretty big
problem as far as I'm concerned so there
will be a lot of work uh for me and
other members namely yunabrina can the
maximum
to work out the specifics and of this
of this mathematical column
thing that allows order to unfold from
chaos
and
most pressingly in my opinion at least
it's it's what I'm supposed to focus on
in terms of my structural flow it is to
work out what this means how social
constraints are enacted and how they
evolve because ultimately the rest is
abstraction this is what has content
this is what allows us to say okay these
are what exists these are the
constraints that shape things and this
is what is their flow
um it is critical from
scientific perspective because it is
what gives me to to listen to her
accounts it is critical from a well
pragmatic perspective because it is uh
what tells us
what world we are in and what is its
flow which is the goal of Kairos
something we'll do with um
uh namely manual job and uh
and
um so basically we will work around the
specific of this
and we will uh if someone decides you to
collaborate please write us we will be
very interested uh because there is a
lot of
all of these problems are big problems
all in state a lot of Firepower
so yeah basically anyone who wants to
who's interested in working on the
specifics with us he's very much invited
to reach out
excellent thank you Alexi apple and
Maxwell for joining thanks everybody for
watching till 34.2
all right it's over thanks
yeah thanks both fellas um
um